My parents were gypsies.
They lived in a camp like this.
They named me Davar.
I travel India entertaining villages
with my monkeys.
Shankar is a 15 year old male.
His wife Gauri is 16
and never leaves Elama, their baby, alone.
Elama was born in March.
All monkeys are born in March.
His mother watches him constantly
and lets no one approach him
except me, of course.
I adore the baby.
It is a true family,
and me, I guess I'm the grandfather
The monkeys have a kingdom,
Kishkindah,
a distant place hidden in the mountains.
In a few days,
we will arrive in this legendary country
that I've been told of
and been dreaming of since my childhood.
Kishkindah has been
the kingdom of monkeys
since the beginning of time
and Hanuman, the monkey god,
its king.
Gauri, Elama, Shankar and I
travel mostly by foot.
From time to time
we take the train.
The conductors do not make us pay
as we amuse the passengers.
My companions
do not enjoy the bustle of the cities,
so I always pass through them quickly.
My family has been living with monkeys
for generations,
as others have with snakes,
bears or elephants.
It is a tradition that is handed down
from father to son.
My ancestors were very poor.
They begged door to door
with their monkeys.
All that changed with my uncle Mamu.
He was the first to teach his monkeys
a bag of tricks
that left entire villages
laughing long after they had gone.
Mamu was a great man.
He taught me to speak with monkeys.
Because of him,
our family escaped poverty.
After several months of work
with my monkeys,
we developed a show
that is very successful.
Everyone is waiting for us
before we arrive in a village.
Shankar is a great comedian
and he loves to make
the audience laugh.
At the sound of my voice,
he knows it is time to start.
I beat my drum.
Shankar hears it.
The spectacle begins.
My monkeys
often keep coins for themselves.
Always the shiniest.
When we pass a shop,
they trade them for a banana
or a piece of cake.
There are monkeys all over India.
They live in the forests, in the fields,
and even come
and steal the food in the cities.
But their roots are in Kishkindah,
the city of monkeys.
Over there the rivers, the lakes,
the forest, the fruit trees
and the mountains
belong to them.
The monkeys protect their kingdom.
This realm extends
beyond the river.
My monkeys feel vulnerable.
The trees are too far away.
I have lived with them
since they were babies.
Before that, I had two other monkeys
my father had given me when I was 15.
We were together for 30 years.
I buried them when they died.
One hears stories of Kishkindah
and the memories of the few people
who have been there
are filled with strange dreams.
The doors of the kingdom
are on the other side of the river.
I have been told
that the gates are guarded,
but I don't know what that means.
Here is the entrance of the kingdom.
Legend says that humans who adventure
here have visions of their previous life.
Could it be that I was a monkey?
Hanuman is the monkey god.
Rama and Sita are the divine couple
most admired by Hindus.
Hanuman is devoted to them,
and in his kingdom,
men follow the example
of the monkey god.
In this temple,
ten girls and two families of monkeys
share their food
and peaceful existence next to Lake Pompa.
They believe that the bottom of the lake
is at the center of the Earth
and dates
from when humans were still gods.
I feel that my monkeys believe
they are human.
When they see themselves in a mirror,
they go crazy.
They can't imagine that they resemble
the wild monkeys we often encounter.
I make my monkeys work every day.
I teach them new tricks.
It takes them a month
to learn a new routine.
Shankar loves to challenge me.
He watches me with his eyes
and tries to apply his law.
It doesn't work.
I'm the boss and he knows it.
When the rehearsal is finished,
Shankar, without being asked,
performs his favorite trick.
Monkeys have extraordinary vision.
Shankar adores pictures.
He examines every detail,
and I often feel
he noticies things I can't see.
Shankar, Gauri, and I
always sleep under the stars.
I lay down on the ground,
but they prefer height.
They fear panthers and tigers.
One night, my monkeys sensed a panther
prowling under the tree
they were perched in.
They were terrified
and escaped from branch to branch.
At dawn, I found them at the centre
of the nearest village.
They had sought refuge
with human beings.
I share all my meals with them.
They eat fruits, vegetables and rice.
Monkeys have sacs in their cheeks
where they can store entire meals.
They eat quickly
because they are afraid of missing food.
We take a bath every morning.
Shankar swims like an otter.
But Gauri and Elama don't like water.
Soon Gauri will be pregnant again
and she will have a daughter.
Gauri is a possessive mother
and will guard Elama as long as possible
until a new baby arrives
and fills her days.
The newborn will become Elama's wife
and they will create a new family.
Not far from here is the heart
of the kingdom, the birthplace of Hanuman.
It is a mountain
that has the shape of a monkey's head.
100 monkeys
and a handful of men live atop it.
Men who worship the monkey god.
Men who understand the monkey language.
To come here with my monkeys
is the most beautiful voyage
I could ever dream about.
There, the monkey
who loved humans, was born
the great monkey
with extraordinary powers.
There some men are celebrating
his existence.
These men are fascinated by monkeys.
They know the story of Hanuman
by heart and talk only about it.
The monkeys living around the temple
hear their stories,
and seem to respond to their words.
There was once a great battle here
between two monkey kings.
A story no one has ever forgotten.
It was the time
when the war divided the monkey people.
The men of this country
followed many paths
to rid themselves of earthly sorrow.
I have found my path:
live with my monkeys,
watch them grow,
protect them
love them.
That's all.